<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Christian amendment delivered in a sermon on New-yeares day 1631. in St Martines Church in Oxford, and now published: by H. Tozer Mr of Arts and Fellow of Exceter Colledge in Oxford</title>
            <author>Tozer, Henry, 1602-1650.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1633</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13850</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24158</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121019</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856210</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856210</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21738</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13850)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21738)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1644:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Christian amendment delivered in a sermon on New-yeares day 1631. in St Martines Church in Oxford, and now published: by H. Tozer Mr of Arts and Fellow of Exceter Colledge in Oxford</title>
                  <author>Tozer, Henry, 1602-1650.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 80 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Lichfield printer to the Famous Vniversity,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1633.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21738:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A CHRISTIAN AMENDMENT Delivered in a Sermon on New-yeares day 1631. in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Martines</hi> Church in <hi>Oxford,</hi> and <hi>now publiſhed:</hi> By H. TOZER M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> of Arts and Fellow of <hi>Exceter</hi> Colledge in <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rev. 21.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>He that ſate vpon the Throne, ſaid; Behold, I make all things new.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 51.10.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Create in me a cleane Heart, o God, and renew a right Spirit within me.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by <hi>Iohn Lichfield</hi> Printer to the Famous Vniverſity. 1633.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21738:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21738:2"/>
            <head>TO THE R. WORSHIPFVLL S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> WALTER PYE Knight, Iuſtice of the Peace in the County of <hi>Hereford;</hi> and Heire to the R. Worſhipfull S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Walter Pye,</hi> K. His Maieſties Attorney in the Court of <hi>Wards.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F any ſhould aske mee (as mine own thoughts doe) vpon what confidence J adventure in this Cenſuring Age, the Publiſhing of this poore enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſcourſe; I would then anſwere
<pb facs="tcp:21738:3"/> them (as now I doe my ſelfe) that, when I review and conſider the Nakedneſſe thereof, I cannot va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue it worthy of the Title of ſuch a <hi>Mite,</hi> as deſeruedly might, when caſt into the Treaſury, finde accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Nor is it my care and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to pleaſe the Humours of thoſe, who can, with ſweet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, ſpend that time in Cenſuring of other mens endeavours, which they might with as good Honesty imploy in the Bettering of their owne. There is a <hi>Carpere vel no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li noſtra vel ede tua,</hi> which I leaue to their Graue conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, vntill ſuch time, as after ſome long-expected <hi>Parturiunt mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> the world happily finde as good cauſe to laugh at their folly,
<pb facs="tcp:21738:3"/> as they at other mens good intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Never was J yet taught ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to flatter, or (without offence given) to feare <hi>Mortality,</hi> much leſſe to make a <hi>Time-ſeruing</hi> Diſpoſition the least part of my happineſſe; and therefore if any ſhall thinke it fit to vilify theſe my weake endeavours, (that there may betweene vs be no loue loſt) I ſhall care as little for their cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, as they doe, or can, for this my labour. Tis <hi>your</hi> deſerving <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> and that in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar towards my ſelfe, which hath (I may truly ſay) enforced me thus farre to appeare vnto the world; and therein to expreſſe that I am ready (though not able) to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence that kinde loue, which by me
<pb facs="tcp:21738:4"/> hath beene receiued from you: The beginning whereof I then happily enjoyed, whiles it pleaſed your good Father, my much Honoured Friend, to commit you vnto my Charge and tuition; in which time, as my ſmall Labours were abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly rewarded by a full Hand, ſo were my true deſires towards <hi>You</hi> further encouraged by many pregnant Teſtimonies of your good and louing dispoſition, which, ſince that time, hath fully appeared in many reall expreſſions. Beſide, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers will confeſſe too that your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing goodneſſe hath beene fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpread in a willing readineſſe towards this your <hi>Colledge;</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring moſt worthily the religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and flouriſhing estate thereof
<pb facs="tcp:21738:4"/> (which ſtands yet (bleſſed be the <hi>Higheſt</hi>) vnqueſtionable) and ſtill thankefully acknowledging their loue towards you, whoſe care hath beene imployed in the gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſame. So that most here haue ſome cauſe, but my ſelfe moſt of all, to honour (at the leaſt in a <hi>true deſire</hi>) the good Deſerts of ſo worthy a friend. For this cauſe deſiring to devote vnto you ſome part of my weake and ſlender labours in testimony of my thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſſe, I haue at the laſt adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured on this ſmall Parcell; the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect whereof will, I know content you well, as being that, which <hi>your ſelfe</hi> with your <hi>vertuous Lady</hi> in the goverment of your family, as good stewards, daily
<pb facs="tcp:21738:5"/> practiſe; only my vnworthy moul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of ſo good à <hi>Matter,</hi> might iuſtly expect to fall ſhort of Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, but that I am well aſſured of your <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> therein too. If any ſhall, for your ſake, be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to afford hereto à favourable Aspect, I ſhall thankefully ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge them my <hi>Courteous</hi> Readers; and to him, that is not purpoſely Curious, ſome ſmall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiting Benefit may happily ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crew. Each man, if not wilfully blinde, may ſee how that <hi>All things</hi> hy Gods dispoſing Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence become daily <hi>new</hi> to <hi>him,</hi> and that tis therefore neceſſary, he ſhould in <hi>Heart</hi> and <hi>Soule</hi> bee <hi>Such</hi> to <hi>God.</hi> However, J am fully aſſured of <hi>Your</hi> Readineſſe in
<pb facs="tcp:21738:5"/> embracing a ſeaſonable <hi>Memen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> tending vnto this purpoſe; E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially ſeeing that as all men haue ſome cauſe thankefully to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the <hi>Renewing</hi> of all things vnto them; ſo <hi>You</hi> much more: Conſidering that, beſides the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant ſufficiency of <hi>worldly rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es</hi> by the Providence of your Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly directed <hi>Father</hi> still flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing towards you, <hi>God</hi> hath ſo quickly inveſted you with <hi>New Dignities</hi> of <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice (Knighthood</hi> and <hi>Iuſtice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi>) imploying you farther in a <hi>new charge,</hi> the <hi>Guidance</hi> of a great <hi>Family,</hi> of which you are made the <hi>Head;</hi> and (which is the Complement of your other feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licities) hath ſeaſonably bleſt you
<pb facs="tcp:21738:6"/> with an hopefull <hi>Sonne;</hi> à <hi>Sonne</hi> borne to you by a ſweetly dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Lady,</hi> who is, both of your Happineſſe a ioyfull Partaker, &amp; alſo a true <hi>Conſort</hi> in your loue to Gods words. So that nothing remaines now, but that you <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue</hi> to endeavour (as you haue begunne) the <hi>Renewing</hi> of your <hi>Heart</hi> in <hi>Thankefulneſſe</hi> vnto that God, who hath ſo plentifully crowned you with thoſe <hi>New bleſſings.</hi> And, that you may thus labour continually to make a ſanctified vſe thereof, for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing of them vnto your ſelfe, (which otherwiſe cannot be look'd for) and alſo the ſetting forth of Gods glory (who beſtowed them on you) you haue for Gods dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting
<pb facs="tcp:21738:6"/> of your heart, the daily prayers of him, who deſires to bee and remaine ever</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in all faithfull reſpects HENRY TOZER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:21738:7"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21738:7"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A CHRISTIAN AMENDMENT.</hi> As it was deliuered in <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines</hi> Church in Oxford.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2. CORINTH. 5.17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Behold All things are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come new.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Text is an argument perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of life, which S. <hi>Paul</hi> doth vrge here to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme what hee had propoſed
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21738:8"/> and proſequuted in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer parts of this Chapter; wherein hee declareth his hope and confidence of that Glory, that was prepared for him, <hi>ver</hi> 1. and further ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth what they ought to bee, who looke to bee partakers thereof; namely ſuch, as la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to bee accepted of God, <hi>v</hi> 9 And that hee might him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe thus appeare, hee endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to approue himſelfe faithfull in the diſpenſation of the Goſpell committed to his truſt; adding further what is required of him and others herevnto; and that is to bee ſuch, who no longer knowe Chriſt according to the fleſh,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21738:8"/> 
               <hi>ver.</hi> 16. but are rather become in him New Creatures: which we muſt be, if We will be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of Him; if partakers of that Glory: for if we looke to haue our habitation in thoſe <hi>buildings, which are eternall in the Heavens, ver.</hi> 1. we muſt bee in Chriſt; and they, which are in Him, muſt be <hi>New Creatures;</hi> for, <hi>Old things are paſſed away;</hi> and, <hi>Behold, all things are become New.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Twere needleſſe to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large an introductory Preface with the different Expoſitions of <hi>Interpreters</hi> on theſe words, in ſhewing what is meant here by <hi>Renewing;</hi> and what by theſe <hi>All things,</hi> which are
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21738:9"/> ſaid to <hi>Become new.</hi> for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſome vnderſtand hereby thoſe <hi>Types</hi> and <hi>Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies</hi> of old, which, ſay they, are now gone and paſt; and ſo we haue in ſtead of an <hi>Old</hi> a <hi>New Testament:</hi> yet if we right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſider their ſeuerall inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretations, we ſhall find them all tending to perſwade a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed ſanctity</hi> in life and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation: which indeed is that wherevnto our <hi>Apoſtle</hi> doth here direct <hi>His</hi> diſcourſe, and which I ſhall accordingly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequute in <hi>Mine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the words we haue
<list>
                  <item>1. An <hi>Invitation;</hi> or a <hi>Stirring</hi> of vs vp to an attentiue Obſeruation; in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21738:9"/> this word, <hi>Behold.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. A <hi>Propoſition</hi> to be conſidered. <hi>All things are become new.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> The firſt word, <hi>Behold,</hi> as it often preſenteth it ſelfe vnto vs in the Scripture, ſo it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly foreſheweth ſomething following, that is worth our notice; that commonly is, may be, or ſhould be knowne of vs: ſuch as indeed is the matter here propoſed; namely this point of <hi>Renewed ſanctitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we looke into the ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall portions of Scripture, which are prefac'd with this <hi>Jntroduction,</hi> this terme <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold,</hi> we ſhall finde the ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21738:10"/> of it to be diuerſe.</p>
            <p>Sometimes we meet with an <hi>Ecce Admirantis,</hi> a <hi>Behold</hi> of <hi>wonder;</hi> as <hi>Joh:</hi> 11.36. <hi>BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HOLD, how hee loued him.</hi> Sometimes an <hi>Ecce Admonen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> a <hi>Behold</hi> of <hi>Caution</hi> or <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition;</hi> as <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.14. <hi>BEHOLD thou art made whole, ſinne no more.</hi> Sometimes an <hi>Ecce Excitantis;</hi> a Behold to Rouze vp and put in remembrance; as 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2. <hi>BEHOLD, now is the accepted time, the day of ſalvation.</hi> And ſometimes an <hi>Ecce certum facientis;</hi> a <hi>Behold</hi> of <hi>Aſſurance:</hi> as <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 1.29. <hi>BEHOLD, J haue giuen you every herbe bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſeed, &amp;c.</hi> Theſe and ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall more be the Acceptions of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21738:10"/> this word, BEHOLD, in the Scripture, ſome whereof are agreeable vnto it, as it is in this Text; which notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding I ſhall not ſeuerally pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequute by way of <hi>Preface</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Matter</hi> following: one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the common vſe of the word wee may obſerue, that, whereas wee haue this <hi>Note</hi> of <hi>Invitation</hi> propoſed in the firſt place, there is ſome matter of conſequence wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of our <hi>Notice</hi> following after; and that is the <hi>Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> before mentioned; namely. <hi>All things are become new,</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:21738:11"/>
            <p>wherein are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable as the <hi>Parts</hi> thereof.
<list>
                  <item>1. The <hi>Subiect;</hi> in this terme, <hi>All things.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. The <hi>Predicate,</hi> or <hi>Attribute. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come New.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> I ſhall ſpeake of theſe two iointly; and therein ſhew how ſome things <hi>Doe,</hi> &amp; how other things <hi>Ought</hi> to <hi>Become New.</hi> This Terme <hi>(All things)</hi> noteth to vs
<list>
                  <item>1 The things that are beſides Man.</item>
                  <item>2 Man himſelfe</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The things beſides Man are
<list>
                  <item>1 <hi>Times</hi> and <hi>Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Thoſe things,</hi> which haue <hi>Times</hi> and <hi>Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> agreeing to them.</item>
               </list>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:21738:11"/> Of all which Wee may gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally conclude in the Phraſe of our <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> that in their Turnes they haue their <hi>Renoua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> they <hi>Become New.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>True it is, Which <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 1.9. that <hi>there is no new thing vnder the Sunne:</hi> that is, there is nothing <hi>now</hi> which hath not beene <hi>hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore;</hi> for ſo it followes <hi>ver.</hi> 10. <hi>Is there any thing whereof it may be ſaid, ſee, this is new? It hath beene already of old time, which was before vs:</hi> ſo that in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect there is nothing <hi>New:</hi> for that were indeede to make the <hi>Creation, Gods</hi> owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per worke, imperfect: yet the things, which are, may bee
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21738:12"/> ſaid to <hi>Become new,</hi> which is the <hi>Phraſe</hi> of our <hi>Apostle</hi> in this place, noting vnto vs a <hi>Renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of the things, which are; and not a <hi>New producing</hi> of the things, that were not.</p>
            <p>In this <hi>Senſe;</hi> firſt <hi>Tymes</hi> and <hi>Seaſons</hi> become <hi>New.</hi> For we know that the <hi>Moone is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for certaine Seaſons, and the Sun knoweth his going downe. Pſal.</hi> 104.19. Whence it comes to paſſe that wee haue <hi>New houres, new daies, new weekes, new months, new yeares:</hi> that is, the <hi>old renewed.</hi> And, as <hi>times</hi> &amp; <hi>ſeaſons</hi> are thus <hi>renewed,</hi> ſo are likewiſe thoſe things, which haue <hi>times</hi> and <hi>ſeaſons</hi> agreeing to them.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:21738:12"/>
            <p>And theſe are
<list>
                  <item>1 <hi>Actions</hi> and <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 The <hi>Fruits</hi> of them.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Both <hi>Renewed:</hi> the firſt for the ſecond; and the ſecond in recompence of the firſt. Thus the labouring man, recalling his former travailes, reioyceth (with the ſunne) to runne his courſe; and at the expected ſeaſon reapeth the <hi>New fruits</hi> of his endeavours; the earth bringing forth <hi>Anew</hi> to him <hi>Graſſe,</hi> and <hi>Corne,</hi> and <hi>Hearbs,</hi> with ſuch other <hi>Fruits</hi> as <hi>God</hi> hath appointed for the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and vſe of <hi>Man.</hi> Thus all things beſides <hi>Man</hi> become <hi>New:</hi> but doth <hi>Man,</hi> for whoſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21738:13"/> ſake all theſe things renewed are become <hi>New</hi> too? Hee ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth or ſhould ſo; for theſe in reſpect of <hi>Him</hi> are but as <hi>ſhaddowes</hi> and <hi>reſemblances;</hi> tis Hee, that is the <hi>Subſtance;</hi> Hee, that muſt make vp the Principall part of theſe ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes leading vs vnto <hi>Newnes</hi> of life.</p>
            <p>If we looke into <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.22. wee ſhall finde that the whole <hi>creation</hi> is ſaid to grone: for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede the <hi>Bondage</hi> of <hi>Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> the <hi>burden</hi> of <hi>ſinne</hi> is very heavy and grievous: but, if wee conſider aright, wee ſhall perceiue, that tis <hi>Man,</hi> which hath drawne this burden vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Creature; tis <hi>Man,</hi> that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21738:13"/> is out of order; <hi>Man,</hi> that is corrupted; <hi>Man,</hi> that is growne as old in ſinne as the world in yeares: and therefore tis <hi>Man,</hi> that muſt be ſet right againe; tis <hi>Hee,</hi> that muſt bee cleanſed; tis <hi>Hee,</hi> euen ſinfull <hi>Man,</hi> that muſt become <hi>New.</hi> And indeede if <hi>Hee</hi> bee once right, then are all things well: if <hi>Man</hi> be once <hi>Renewed,</hi> there is nothing any longer <hi>Old:</hi> for <hi>Hee</hi> hath, as it were, all other things contained in <hi>Him;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as he is called) that <hi>Micro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſme,</hi> or <hi>leſſer world,</hi> the <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome</hi> of nature and of the workes thereof; ſo that if <hi>Hee</hi> bee New, then are all things ſo.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:21738:14"/>
            <p>Now <hi>Man</hi> is ſaid to become <hi>New;</hi> firſt <hi>Inwardly</hi> in the <hi>Roote,</hi> by Iuſtification; and thus are <hi>Infidels,</hi> men not called before, ſaid to become <hi>New,</hi> when by the power of Gods ſpirit they are converted to the faith of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Next, <hi>Outwardly</hi> in the <hi>Fruite,</hi> by ſanctity and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in life; and thus are the <hi>Regenerate,</hi> the Iuſtified mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt, againe ſaid to become <hi>New,</hi> when, leauing the deceitfulneſſe and allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſinne, they devote themſelues vnto God in a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed converſation, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming their liues vnto His word as the rule thereof. This
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21738:14"/> 
               <hi>Renouation,</hi> this <hi>becoming new,</hi> this <hi>Amending</hi> of our liues in the feare of God is that, which here I intend breifly to vrge; and, for the more vſefull diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch thereof, ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour plainely to ſhew.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> why wee muſt become New.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The <hi>Manner</hi> how, or the <hi>Particulars,</hi> wherein this <hi>Reno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> ſhould conſiſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The <hi>Meanes,</hi> whereby the ſame may be effected.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The <hi>Fruits,</hi> which will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe therevpon.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of this duty will appeare from the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the ſeverall vrging reaſons perſwading vs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21738:15"/> And theſe may bee drawne.</p>
            <p>Firſt, from thoſe <hi>examples,</hi> that are afforded to vs in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it ſelfe. The <hi>Sunne,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out failing, meaſureth out vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs <hi>New daies</hi> &amp; <hi>New yeares;</hi> the <hi>Moone New months:</hi> and the <hi>Earth,</hi> for our Inſtruction as Well as profit, is in the apoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſeaſon adorned with <hi>New fruits:</hi> which indeede are but as ſo many reſemblances, to ſhew vnto vs, what <hi>Man</hi> ſhould be; <hi>A new creature.</hi> It is a rule of the Philoſopher, that <hi>In natura nihil eſt ſuperfluum,</hi> there is nothing in nature ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous: which rule is here made vnqueſtionably true;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21738:15"/> for in nature there is nothing, but ſome good vſe may bee made thereof; wee hauing therein ſo many Arguments preſſing vs to the <hi>Renewing</hi> of our Converſations. For if God for <hi>Mans</hi> vſe and profit cauſe all theſe things in their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed ſeaſons to be <hi>Renewed,</hi> ſhall <hi>Man,</hi> for whoſe benefit all theſe things <hi>Renewed</hi> are, remaine <hi>Old</hi> ſtill, and haue nothing in him <hi>New,</hi> except it be ſome <hi>new ſinnes; new Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, new prophanations, new mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, new blasphemies;</hi> or the <hi>old renewed,</hi> to provoke God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh? Nature it ſelfe will teach you, ſaith S. <hi>Paul,</hi> that <hi>if a man weare long haire it is a ſhame vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21738:16"/> him.</hi> 1 Cor. 11.14 Wee may vſe the like argument and ſay; that, if any man grow <hi>Old</hi> in <hi>Sinne,</hi> as he muſt in <hi>yeares,</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture will accuſe him of a ſhamefull neglect, in not hau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing better learned <hi>God,</hi> and the neceſſity of a <hi>renewed</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation before <hi>Him,</hi> even from his <hi>Workes</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> which are made therefore manifeſt to him to guide and inſtruct him; for Nature doth freely offer it ſelfe, as a guide vnto vs, and blind are they, who ſee not how to follow it. It is, we know, a common ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, that God hath two bookes to inſtruct vs. The one is his booke of Scripture,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21738:16"/> Wherein we may (and happy are they, which therein daily doe) reade and conſider the ſumme of their Duty and the myſtery of their redemption. The ſecond is his booke of Nature, written with his owne hand in the ſixe daies of the <hi>Creation:</hi> a volume as large as the world it ſelfe; but every <hi>Page</hi> therein plainely teaching <hi>man</hi> the knowledge of God, and the neceſſity of his owne becomming <hi>new</hi> in his ſight. And S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſeemes to make <hi>this</hi> the very drift of our Apoſtle in this <hi>text;</hi> S. <hi>Paul</hi> (ſaith he) draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a new argument from na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it ſelfe, to lift vp the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21738:17"/> mindes of theſe <hi>Corinthians</hi> from the things here below to God aboue, the maker of them, to teach them from theſe what they ſhould be to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Him,</hi> namely, in Chriſt <hi>new creatures.</hi> The neceſſity of which <hi>Renovation</hi> will farther appeare by a ſecond reaſon, drawne from the <hi>Expectation</hi> of God requiring it of vs. <hi>God expecteth,</hi> and therefore tis ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that wee ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>new creatures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that God expecteth from vs a renewing of our converſations, a <hi>reforming</hi> of our liues, wee may plainely reade in his other <hi>Booke,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, namely his
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21738:17"/> 
               <hi>booke</hi> of <hi>Scripture;</hi> wherein we ſhall meete with <hi>Precepts,</hi> and <hi>Threatnings</hi> and <hi>Judgements,</hi> and <hi>promiſes,</hi> and the <hi>Mercies</hi> of God: all which are but as ſo many <hi>calls</hi> and <hi>warnings,</hi> &amp; gratious <hi>invitations</hi> to an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of life.</p>
            <p>Firſt, a <hi>precept</hi> or <hi>Commande</hi> we haue, recorded by <hi>S. Paul</hi> Epheſ. 4.24. where the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle telleth vs, that <hi>wee are taught in Christ to put on the new man, which after God is created in Righteouſneſse &amp; true holineſſe; wherefore</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>putting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way lying ſpeake every man truth; be angry and ſinne not; giue not place vnto the Divill, &amp;c.</hi> in all which we are by the <hi>H.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21738:18"/> Ghoſt</hi> plainely <hi>commanded</hi> to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new</hi> our converſation in true Holineſſe and righteouſneſſe before God. And the same <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle</hi> will farther tell vs 1. Tim. 1.5. that <hi>the end of the commandement is Charity out of a pure Heart, and a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and faith vnfained.</hi> So that where a <hi>Precept</hi> or <hi>Commande</hi> is, there muſt bee Obedience; eſpecially when the <hi>commande</hi> proceedeth from God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, whom we cannot diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey, but with the loſſe of our firſt loue, and the hazard of our owne ſafety: when God therefore requireth vs to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>new</hi> men, as here and elſewhere he often doth, wee
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21738:18"/> carefully ſhould endeavour to be ſuch: for <hi>precipientium Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritas &amp; preceptorum qualitas attendenda eſt,</hi> faith <hi>Bernard:</hi> the Authority of the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and the condition of the commande it ſelfe are dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently to be regarded. Now God, who requireth this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty at our hands, is that <hi>Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> which knoweth no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall; and his commande is of that condition, that as it tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to his owne glory, ſo is it likewiſe for our good and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: wherefore, a God <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecteth,</hi> ſo it is neceſſary in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the <hi>Precept</hi> that wee ſhould become <hi>new.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, that God expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21738:19"/> and requireth this of vs will farther appeare by his <hi>Threatnings</hi> againſt ſinners, &amp; his <hi>Iudgements</hi> vpon man for <hi>ſinne. Woe,</hi> ſaith the Lord. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 5.18. there is his threatning. A <hi>woe</hi> there is for <hi>Corazin</hi> and <hi>Bethſaida;</hi> for <hi>Edom, Moab</hi> &amp; <hi>Nebo:</hi> A <hi>woe</hi> for the <hi>Idole ſhea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phards</hi> and blinde <hi>Guides;</hi> for the Deceitfull <hi>Lawyer</hi> and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriticall <hi>Phariſee;</hi> and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally a <hi>woe</hi> for all, that ſinne with greedyneſſe, and ſtill draw iniquity with coards of vanity. Neither is there a bare pronouncing of <hi>woe,</hi> but a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery inflicted too; <hi>Iudgement</hi> as well as <hi>threatnings: Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> with the citties a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21738:19"/> them, <hi>ſet forth for an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, ſuffering the vengeance of eternall fire Iude</hi> 7. all which <hi>woes</hi> and <hi>Iudgements,</hi> with many more, are written for our Admonition, that wee ſhould not <hi>luſt</hi> as they <hi>luſted,</hi> nor be <hi>Idolaters,</hi> nor commit <hi>fornication,</hi> nor <hi>tempt</hi> Chriſt, nor <hi>murmure.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.6. So that the <hi>threatnings</hi> and <hi>Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of God vpon ſinners, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in the Scripture, were not only for the Puniſhment and Deſtruction of thoſe, on whom they fell, but alſo for warnings vnto vs, to driue vs, with <hi>Lot,</hi> out of wicked <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> to terrifie vs from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighting in ſinne, and to ſhew
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21738:20"/> what we muſt be, if wee will be accepted of Him; <hi>New crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</hi> Wherefore, as God <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth,</hi> ſo tis neceſſary, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his <hi>Threatnings</hi> and <hi>Judgements,</hi> that wee ſhould become <hi>New.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, As in the two for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, ſo doth he likewiſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt his expectation in his <hi>Promiſes</hi> and <hi>Mercies,</hi> which are as ſo many gratious <hi>Invita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> to become <hi>New creatures.</hi> To reckon vp all the <hi>promiſes</hi> of God were farre to exceede. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> hath recorded one, which may ſerue for all the reſt. <hi>Come out, &amp; bee yee ſeparate, and touch not the vncleane thing,</hi> ſaith the Lord; <hi>and</hi> I <hi>will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21738:20"/> you, and will be your father, and yee ſhall be my Sonnes and Daughters,</hi> ſaith the Lord Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty. 2. Cor: 6.18. If God be once pleaſed to be our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, wee can then pray for no more, then to become o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient children and to bee thankefull: this hee hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to bee, if wee become <hi>New creatures</hi> before him; and his promiſes faile not; for his <hi>Mercy</hi> will make them good, and that laſteth to a thouſand generations of them that loue and feare him <hi>Exod:</hi> 20.6. Hence Eternall life is ſaid to be the end of the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements. Our obedience in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede is the firſt end thereof,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21738:21"/> as I noted before: but that is directed to a ſecond, namely our ſalvation; and both vnto a third, as the chiefe and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall, which is Gods Glory. In reſpect of our ſelues then the end of the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is ſalvation, which God is pleaſed, not only to <hi>Promiſe,</hi> but alſo in <hi>mercy</hi> to make good vnto vs vpon our <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> in converſation: yea there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are his <hi>promiſes</hi> and <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> made knowne to vs, that ſo with a chearfull readineſſe wee might become <hi>new crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> before Him: for that is the vſe which S. <hi>Paul</hi> makes of them, as wee may reade 2. Cor. 7.1. Hauing therefore
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21738:21"/> theſe <hi>Promiſes,</hi> ſaith he, (name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that <hi>God will bee our Father, &amp;c.</hi> as it is in the end of the precedent chapter) what muſt wee therevpon doe? <hi>Let vs cleanſe our ſelues from all filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, perfecting holineſſe in the feare of God.</hi> It is doubtleſſe (if wee know it) our great happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that wee haue ſo many <hi>Promiſes</hi> and <hi>Mercies</hi> propoſed to vs: and wee muſt farther know, that tis but our boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den duty to embrace them, and to make a ſanctified vſe thereof. Hauing therefore ſuch gratious Invitations to become <hi>new creatures</hi> in the ſight of God, let vs not caſt off his free <hi>promiſes</hi> and <hi>mercies</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:21738:22"/> by growing <hi>Old</hi> in our ſinnes; but let vs rather turne to Him, who ſo <hi>lovingly</hi> inviteth vs, &amp; who therein plainely ſhewes, that he deſireth not our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, but that we ſhould <hi>Returne</hi> and <hi>Liue:</hi> this deſire of His includeth his <hi>expectation</hi> of our obedience. Wherefore, as God <hi>expecteth,</hi> ſo tis neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary in regard of his <hi>promiſes</hi> and <hi>mercies,</hi> that wee ſhould become <hi>New.</hi> Thus haue I laid open my ſecond <hi>Reaſon,</hi> taken from the expectation of God himſelfe; which is clearely manifeſt (as it hath beene ſhewed) in His <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, threatnings, iudgements, promiſes,</hi> and <hi>mercies;</hi> by all
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21738:22"/> which wee may ſee that God requires, and that tis <hi>therefore</hi> vndoubtedly neceſſary that wee become <hi>new creatures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly this neceſſity will yet farther appeare by a 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
               <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> drawne from our <hi>vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> to the faith of Chriſt, and our <hi>Justification</hi> by his merits; the very end whereof (next vnto Gods glory and the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of our ſoules) is the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment</hi> of our liues.</p>
            <p>What is our happineſſe, in that wee are called to bee the members of Chriſt, we ſhall never fully vnderſtand till we come at the laſt to receiue the Crowne thereof, when wee ſhall <hi>ſee God face to face, and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21738:23"/> knowe him as we are knowne:</hi> yet may wee in <hi>ſome meaſure</hi> bee ſenſible of it; for wee know that we are <hi>Thereby</hi> freed from that Egyptian bondage and Thraldome of ſinne, as S. <hi>Luke</hi> for our comfort, hath recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the words of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. <hi>Luke</hi> 4.18, 19. This day, ſaith Chriſt, is <hi>This Scripture fulfilled in your eares:</hi> but what Scripture? That, which the Prophet <hi>Jſaiah</hi> had foretold of him; namely, that <hi>Hee was ſent to heale the broken hearted, to preach deliverance vnto the captiues, and recouering of ſight to the blinde, and to ſet at liberty thoſe which are bruiſed:</hi> all which benefits acrue to thoſe that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21738:23"/> are <hi>called</hi> and made the Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied members of Chriſt. Wee then haue receiued liberty, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made Heires of the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace: but to what end? that wee may doe what we liſt, and walke as we pleaſe? Shall wee freely ſinne, becauſe wee are vnder grace? <hi>S. Paul</hi> will take that off with a <hi>God forbid. Rom</hi> 6.15. for that were to turne the grace of God into wantonneſſe, and to <hi>vſe</hi> our liberty, wherevnto we are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, or rather to <hi>Abuſe</hi> it for an occaſion to the fleſh <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.13. We rather ſhould walke as S. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorteth his Epheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 1. <hi>worthy of the vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation wherewith wee are called:</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:21738:24"/> wee are made the members of Chriſt, the adopted ſonnes of God, therefore (to make good our calling) ought wee to liue as His children, His ſervants; not ſeruing our ſelues in the <hi>fleſh,</hi> but him in the <hi>ſpirit:</hi> for the immediate end of our <hi>converſion</hi> is and ought to be a regularity and reforming of our <hi>Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> and therefore in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect tis likewiſe neceſſary that wee ſhould become <hi>new.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, A fourth reaſon (and that vrgent enough) to proue and perſwade the ſame, may be taken from the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of our owne Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for, if wee looke well at
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21738:24"/> home, wee ſhall every one of vs finde within himſelfe à <hi>Soule</hi> that needs <hi>Repentance;</hi> &amp; which may therefore iuſtly call vpon vs for this <hi>Renovati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> That wee daily ſinne, I ſuppoſe no man ſo much as doubteth, eſpecially if he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, what it is to be the <hi>ſonne</hi> of a <hi>tranſgreſſing Adam:</hi> for, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though a man may bee <hi>ſine querelâ,</hi> yet he cannot bee <hi>ſine peccato;</hi> as S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſpeaketh: ſo liue hee may, as that the world ſhall haue but little to ſay vnto him; hee may carry himſelfe without offending a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and ſo be accounted, with <hi>Zacharias, blameleſſe. Luke</hi> 1.16. Thus he may bee <hi>ſine querelâ,</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:21738:25"/> not deſeruing any complaint of man againſt him; yet can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not he be <hi>ſine peccato,</hi> without offence againſt God: for <hi>Hee</hi> will ſtill behold iniquity, and that manifold, even in his beſt Actions; which indeede, without the Advantage of a gratious acceptance, could be in themſelues nothing but <hi>Sinne.</hi> Now thoſe ſinnes, whereof wee ſtand guilty and which wee daily commit (though ſometimes we know it not) What are they but as ſo many <hi>partition-walls</hi> betweene <hi>God</hi> and <hi>vs,</hi> as S. <hi>Bernard</hi> calls them; which hinder vs from ſending vp acceptable prayers vnto Him, and ſtop likewiſe
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21738:25"/> the beames of his gratious fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour from deſcending downe vpon vs. <hi>Christ</hi> indeede hath taken away that great wall of <hi>ſeparation,</hi> that our ſinnes had made, but, if wee rightly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, wee ſhall ſee that by our daily tranſgreſſions Wee doe but ſeeke, as farre as in vs ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, to build it vp againe: and, while wee thereby keepe off the mercies of God from vs, wee kindle in our hearts no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but ſinfull Luſts &amp; De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, which are a fire, faith <hi>Chryſoſtome, Lachrimis extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guendus,</hi> that is to bee quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched by the <hi>teares of repentance:</hi> And, becauſe we daily ſinne, therefore, ſaith one, our
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:21738:26"/> whole life ſhould bee accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted but as one day of <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> and this <hi>Repentance</hi> the worke of that <hi>whole</hi> day. And ſurely while wee neglect this, wee either doe or would, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get our owne cuſtomes; which might, if well conſidered, bee very vſefull to put vs vpon this courſe of <hi>Renovation:</hi> for becauſe our Hands daily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract ſoyle; and our houſes duſt, and ſometimes decay too; doe wee not therefore daily <hi>ſweepe</hi> the one &amp; <hi>Cleanſe</hi> the other, and <hi>Repaire</hi> and <hi>Build,</hi> as need requires? hence then let vs admoniſh &amp; teach our ſelues: we <hi>ſweepe,</hi> and <hi>waſh,</hi> and <hi>repaire,</hi> and all becauſe
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:21738:26"/> there is neede: Looke now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thine owne <hi>Soule,</hi> ſearch the corners of thy heart, and (if thou haue a Chriſtian eye) ſee What <hi>contractions</hi> are there, what multiplied <hi>Heapes</hi> of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, what <hi>Ruines,</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayes: Darkeneſſe</hi> in the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, <hi>Perverſeneſſe</hi> in the will, and affections, good de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires well nigh loſt: and then tell mee (if thou haue a chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an feeling too) whether now thou haſt not cauſe enough to <hi>ſweepe,</hi> and <hi>cleanſe,</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire</hi> thy heart by a daily <hi>Reno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi> The world perhaps may tell thee that all is well; yet deceiue not thy ſoule; for there is a <hi>Conſcience</hi> within,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:21738:27"/> which cannot be bribed, that will tell thee tis otherwiſe: and, <hi>ſi conſcientia criminis mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det laus mundi parumprodeſt:</hi> to be ſoothed vp by ſinfull men, like vnto thy ſelfe, will but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle availe thee, when thine owne conſcience ſhall accuſe thee of tranſgreſſion, &amp; plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhew that there is need of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment. Wherefore, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of our owne <hi>ſoules,</hi> and the <hi>ſinfulneſſe</hi> thereof, it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary that wee ſhould become <hi>New.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly, a fifth reaſon to proue this neceſſity may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from our vtter <hi>Indispoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> to receiue any future good vntill ſuch time, as wee bee
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:21738:27"/> thus <hi>Renewed.</hi> It is a rule in <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> that <hi>Intus apparens prohibet alienum:</hi> That, which is firſt in, doth commonly keepe out the reſt. If the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell can but get and retaine his hold in our heart, he Will then ſuffer none to come there but ſuch as are like himſelfe. Firſt therefore wee muſt <hi>out</hi> with <hi>Him,</hi> &amp; then ſhall good Inſtructions take place the better, and become the more profitable vnto vs. So much our Saviour Chriſt hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>Matt:</hi> 9.16. <hi>No man,</hi> ſaith <hi>Hee, putteth new cloath vnto an old garment,</hi> for then is the rent made worſe; neither doe wee put <hi>New wine into old bottles,</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:21738:28"/> for then ſhall they breake, and both periſh; but <hi>New wine must be put into new bottles, and both are preſerved. Christ</hi> and <hi>Belial, ſanctity</hi> and <hi>ſinne,</hi> the <hi>Divill</hi> and <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> can never dwell together; but there muſt, there will be a <hi>Rent,</hi> a <hi>Diviſion</hi> betweene them: <hi>Out</hi> therefore With thoſe <hi>Old</hi> ſins, which haue dwelt ſo long in thy heart, that ſo thou maiſt the better receiue and make vſe of thoſe good <hi>Motions</hi> and <hi>Jnſtructions,</hi> which tend to the Perfecting of Holineſſe; and which otherwiſe will be vnto Thee but as ſo many <hi>Pearles</hi> caſt before <hi>ſwine:</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in this reſpect it is like-Wiſe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:21738:28"/> neceſſary that we ſhould become <hi>New.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixtly, A ſixt (and the laſt) Reaſon to vrge the ſame may bee taken from the common Practiſe of our Adverſary the Divill. <hi>Hee</hi> is that <hi>envious</hi> man, which ſoweth in the field of our hearts the Tares of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption whiles wee ſleepe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely in our ſinnes; His <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſes</hi> to withdraw vs from the performance of this Duty, are as many, as wee can meete with Helpes to further vs in it; and, He being (as he ever hath beene) a profeſſed enimy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all goodneſſe, wee may e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>Thence</hi> learne and know, that tis moſt neceſſary wee
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:21738:29"/> ſhould endeavour to become <hi>New creatures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that now if any ſhall aske, why hee muſt amend his converſation? I will anſwere Him, that, which way ſoever hee lookes, hee ſhall meete with ſome Argument to vrge the Neceſſity. If <hi>aboue</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; <hi>There</hi> is a <hi>God</hi> who <hi>calls</hi> for it by his <hi>Precepts,</hi> who <hi>Warneth</hi> &amp; <hi>Driueth</hi> vs to it by his <hi>Threatnings</hi> and <hi>Iudgements;</hi> and who <hi>Allureth</hi> vnto the ſame by his <hi>Promiſes</hi> and <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</hi> If <hi>within</hi> himſelfe, <hi>there</hi> is a <hi>Soule,</hi> that needes it, and a <hi>Conſcience</hi> that will tell him ſo. If <hi>below</hi> himſelfe, yea if <hi>round about</hi> him, <hi>there</hi> ſtand the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:21738:29"/> 
               <hi>workes</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> to leade him to it; and <hi>there</hi> is likewiſe a <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill,</hi> that ſtill <hi>Oppoſeth</hi> &amp; ſeekes to divert him from it. So that in regard of God requiring it, and our owne <hi>Soules</hi> wanting it, and the <hi>Divills</hi> deſtructiue policies againſt vs to prevent and withſtand it, tis vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly neceſſary that wee ſhould by all good meanes la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to become <hi>New crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</hi> Thus haue wee ſeene, by way of <hi>Perſwation,</hi> the <hi>neceſſity</hi> of becoming <hi>new.</hi> In the next place wee are to conſider, by way of <hi>Direction,</hi> the <hi>Manner how,</hi> and the <hi>Meanes whereby</hi> the ſame may be effected.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, to become
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:21738:30"/> 
               <hi>new</hi> in this place (as before hath beene ſhewed) is to <hi>Amend</hi> our liues, to <hi>Reforme</hi> whatſoever hath bin amiſſe in our conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation: which indeede is the ſame with that Duty of <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> that is ſo much preached and ſpoken of, and ſo little practiſed. To a right perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance whereof; things (ſaith <hi>Piſcator</hi>) are required.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Displicentia vitae anteactae;</hi> A diſliking of our former life.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Studium Gratiae;</hi> A deſire of Gods mercy and grace for the diſpoſing of our hearts to a <hi>Better</hi> converſation.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Propoſitum ſancte progredien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di;</hi> A firme reſolution, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to <hi>Beginne,</hi> but alſo to <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:21738:30"/> in a better courſe. So that, if wee as wee ought, will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>New</hi> indeede, we muſt haue reſpect vnto the Time <hi>paſt, preſent</hi> and to <hi>come.</hi> In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the <hi>Time paſt,</hi> there muſt be an <hi>hearty ſorrow,</hi> vpon due examination, for whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hath beene done Amiſſe before: in reſpect of the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,</hi> a <hi>diligent endeavour</hi> to bee <hi>better ſetled;</hi> &amp;, for that, which is <hi>to come,</hi> a <hi>Reſolute purpoſe</hi> to <hi>continue</hi> ſo vnto the end. For to be <hi>Renewed preſuppoſeth</hi> a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouall</hi> of what is <hi>Old;</hi> therefore muſt wee caſt away our <hi>Old</hi> ſinnes: it <hi>conſiſteth</hi> in a better <hi>compoſing</hi> and <hi>ſetting in order;</hi> Therefore muſt wee labour to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:21738:31"/> bee furniſhed with <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> inſtead of them: And it <hi>requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth</hi> a <hi>continuall care</hi> that wee grow not <hi>Old</hi> in our ſinnes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; and Therefore like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe muſt wee reſolue to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine <hi>ſuch</hi> in the <hi>future,</hi> as we deſire to become in the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The two former (namely, the <hi>Renouncing</hi> of <hi>ſinne,</hi> and the <hi>entertaining</hi> of <hi>ſanctity</hi> in the roome thereof) muſt be done not in one <hi>Part</hi> alone but in the <hi>whole:</hi> there muſt be a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>renewing</hi> of the <hi>whole</hi> man; of the <hi>Heart,</hi> and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever proceedeth from it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Renewing</hi> or <hi>Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of the <hi>Heart</hi> is tearmed by
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:21738:31"/> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> the <hi>circumciſion</hi> of it: which is that <hi>circumciſion</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, that God doth now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire at our hands; for true <hi>Circumciſion</hi> now is not in the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> but <hi>that in the spirit.</hi> Rom. 2.29. And indeede if wee will make right vſe of our Saviours <hi>circumciſion</hi> (which wee <hi>this day</hi> celebrate) wee muſt learne and labour to bee Circumciſed in our Hearts, &amp; ſo to become <hi>New creatures In</hi> and <hi>To</hi> him.</p>
            <p>Now the <hi>Heart</hi> (according to the Scripturall acception of the word) includeth the <hi>will</hi> and all the <hi>Affections</hi> of man: ſo that, if wee deſire to become fully <hi>New,</hi> we muſt
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:21738:32"/> in the firſt place haue <hi>New thoughts, new Meditations, new deſires;</hi> and then like <hi>Fruits</hi> proceeding from them; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>new words,</hi> and <hi>new actions:</hi> for, as wee daily ſinne both in our <hi>Thoughts,</hi> and <hi>words,</hi> and <hi>Deedes,</hi> ſo muſt there be a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing,</hi> a <hi>Reforming</hi> of them all, if wee will become <hi>perfectly New.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To endeavour the <hi>renewing</hi> of our <hi>words</hi> and <hi>deedes,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a former <hi>Refining</hi> of our <hi>Thoughts,</hi> were but to <hi>Pretend,</hi> not ſeriouſly to <hi>Purpoſe</hi> a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novation:</hi> for <hi>Cogitatio orationis fons est;</hi> our <hi>Thoughts</hi> are the Fountaine, from which our <hi>words</hi> &amp; <hi>actions</hi> flow: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:21738:32"/> if <hi>They</hi> bee ſtill troubled with the <hi>Corruption</hi> of ſinne; <hi>Theſe</hi> cannot runne ſo cleare as to haue no <hi>Tincture</hi> of impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Or (if you will) good <hi>Thoughts</hi> are vnto <hi>Like words and actions,</hi> even as the Coale vnto the Flame; if the <hi>one</hi> bee extinguiſhed, the <hi>other</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares not. Wherefore, that wee may become <hi>new</hi> as wee ought, wee muſt in the firſt place <hi>reforme</hi> our <hi>thoughts</hi> &amp; <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires:</hi> and therein we ſhall finde matter enough to worke on.</p>
            <p>When I was a <hi>Child,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi> 1 Cor. 13.11. I thought as a Child, yea and <hi>did</hi> ſo too. The caſe is ours, but in a farre greater meaſure of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity:
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:21738:33"/> for, when he became a <hi>Man,</hi> he put away <hi>Childiſh</hi> things, as <hi>Himſelfe</hi> there teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies: But wee, that after a long <hi>Jnſtitution</hi> (in a glorious ſunne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine of the Goſpell) ſhould now bee <hi>compleate men,</hi> fall backe againe to bee <hi>Babes</hi> in Chriſt, and to <hi>Thinke</hi> as <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren;</hi> to imploy our <hi>Thoughts</hi> on <hi>Vanities</hi> and <hi>Folly;</hi> to <hi>thinke</hi> with thoſe Pſal. 49 11. that our houſes ſhall continue for ever; and, with <hi>Haman, Eſther</hi> 6.6 to ſet on worke our <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations</hi> about expected Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and Preferments; who <hi>Thought in his Heart</hi> (ſaith the Text) <hi>to whome would the King delight to doe Honour more then
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:21738:33"/> to my ſelfe.</hi> Neither doe we on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thinke as Children in Chriſt (that is not the worſt) but ſometimes too as men, that haue no reference to him; as <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> as men <hi>without God;</hi> when <hi>God is not in all our thoughts:</hi> as the <hi>Prophet David</hi> ſpeaketh Pſal. 10.4. Such are our <hi>thoughts</hi> of <hi>malice</hi> and <hi>mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der;</hi> when, with <hi>Cain,</hi> we thinke to cut off righteous <hi>Abell;</hi> and with <hi>Jſhbibenob,</hi> to ſlay <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.16. <hi>Such</hi> are our thoughts of <hi>Rebellion,</hi> when wee <hi>Curſe</hi> the Lords <hi>Annoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> in our Thoughts. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10 20. Such are our <hi>Thoughts</hi> of <hi>Adultery</hi> and <hi>Vncleaneſſe;</hi> when wee <hi>Thinke</hi> on a wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:21738:34"/> Harlot to <hi>Luſt</hi> after her. <hi>Matt.</hi> 5. <hi>verſ.</hi> 28. <hi>Such</hi> are our <hi>thoughts</hi> of <hi>deceite</hi> and <hi>falſhood,</hi> when we <hi>imagine</hi> in our hearts <hi>miſchievous plots</hi> and <hi>devices</hi> to <hi>circumvent</hi> our neighbours. <hi>Such</hi> be our vniuſt <hi>Thoughts</hi> of <hi>Covetuouſneſſe</hi> and <hi>Diſcontent;</hi> when with wicked <hi>Ahab,</hi> wee are <hi>troubled</hi> on our beds how to get <hi>Naboths</hi> vineyard. 1 King: 21.4. and <hi>Such</hi> are our <hi>Prophane thoughts</hi> againſt <hi>God</hi> himſelfe, when we <hi>Thinke Him</hi> (though in vaine) to be <hi>ſuch a one, as our ſelues,</hi> that can bee deceiued: <hi>Pſal:</hi> 50.21. And theſe <hi>Thoughts</hi> of ours al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Divell <hi>directly</hi> ſee not, (for that belongs to <hi>God</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:21738:34"/> alone) yet our owne woefull experience can ſufficiently tell vs, that hee often fitteth vs with occaſions anſwerable therevnto; and we may <hi>thence</hi> imagine, that (by obſeruing our temper and complexion) Hee comes very neere vnto them. Matter enough then we haue to be reformed in our <hi>thoughts,</hi> and the <hi>neceſſity</hi> is no leſſe <hi>vrgent.</hi> But happily a <hi>car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall worldly minded man</hi> will ſay, I may ſecurely <hi>thus Thinke</hi> and <hi>Meditate,</hi> becauſe the World perceiueth it not: be it ſo; yet <hi>God</hi> doth, which is more: but however; Dareſt thou to boaſt hereof, and to ſay vnto the World, that <hi>ſuch</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:21738:35"/> as theſe, are thy <hi>Thoughts</hi> and <hi>Deſires?</hi> If not, then let the <hi>Fathers</hi> Rule bee thy Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancer, <hi>Quicquid pudet dicere, pudeat &amp; cogitare:</hi> If thou bluſh (as doubtleſſe thou wilt) to make it openly knowne, that thy <hi>Drifts</hi> and <hi>Intentions</hi> are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Bloody,</hi> or <hi>vnchaſt,</hi> or <hi>Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious,</hi> or <hi>Deceitfull,</hi> or <hi>Coveting,</hi> or <hi>Prophane,</hi> then forbeare and tremble to <hi>Thinke</hi> of theſe things in thy Heart. But <hi>How</hi> (ſaith the <hi>well diſpoſed Chriſtian</hi>) ſhall I <hi>Rectify</hi> and <hi>Renew</hi> my <hi>Thoughts</hi> being thus perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? <hi>Pliny</hi> will giue thee a good rule for <hi>that: Homines aut Mortalitatem, aut Jmmortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem cogitare debent,</hi> ſaith hee;
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:21738:35"/> men ſhould ever be <hi>Thinking</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of their <hi>Mortality,</hi> or of their <hi>Jmmortality.</hi> If of the <hi>firſt;</hi> then <hi>Bethinke</hi> thy ſelfe (as S. <hi>Bernard</hi> directeth thee) 1. <hi>Vnde venis,</hi> whence thou art derived; namely, from <hi>ſinfull Adam, &amp; erubeſce,</hi> and bluſh at thy fall. 2. <hi>Vbi ſis,</hi> where thou art, namely, in a <hi>vale</hi> of <hi>iniquity; &amp; ingenmiſse,</hi> and ſo <hi>bewaile</hi> thine owne <hi>miſery</hi> 3 <hi>Quo va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis,</hi> whether thou muſt; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, vnto the <hi>Graue;</hi> &amp; <hi>Contre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſce,</hi> and then <hi>Tremble</hi> at thy Danger. And thus ſhall thy <hi>Thoughts</hi> make thee truly <hi>Humble</hi> in the ſight of God. But, if, on the other ſide, thou <hi>Thinke</hi> and <hi>Meditate</hi> of thy
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:21738:36"/> 
               <hi>Immortality,</hi> of thy <hi>Soule,</hi> which muſt remaine ſomewhere for ever; then lift vp thy heart in pious <hi>Thoughts</hi> and <hi>Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> to <hi>Him,</hi> that hath <hi>redeemed</hi> it; to <hi>Him,</hi> that <hi>Sanctifies;</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> that muſt <hi>receiue</hi> it: <hi>Thinke</hi> then ſeriouſly of thy waies, &amp; turne ſpeedily vnto His Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies; as <hi>David</hi> hath dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted thee by his owne exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.59. For There ſhalt thou learne to <hi>Thinke</hi> no more of <hi>malice,</hi> or <hi>luſt,</hi> or <hi>deceit,</hi> or <hi>coveting,</hi> or <hi>Prophanation;</hi> but rather to ſettle thy <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations</hi> on <hi>Sobriety</hi> towards thy <hi>ſelfe;</hi> on <hi>Loue</hi> and <hi>Mercy,</hi> &amp; <hi>Iustice</hi> towards thy <hi>Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours;</hi> and on <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:21738:36"/> towards <hi>God. Thus</hi> we muſt <hi>Thinke</hi> and <hi>Meditate,</hi> if we will haue right, if <hi>New thoughts:</hi> for <hi>Turpes Cogitationes vitare non poteſt, qui Honeſtas non habet:</hi> if wee Thinke not of Good things, wee ſhall of <hi>Bad;</hi> if <hi>God</hi> be not in the Heart, the Divell will be there: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if thou wilt be happy in the <hi>One,</hi> caſt out the <hi>other. Thinke</hi> no more, as thou haſt done, to thriue by Deceiuing; <hi>Thinke</hi> no longer to make thy ſelfe ſecure by intrapping, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnaring, and circumventing others; <hi>Imagine</hi> not to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine thine owne credit by ſlandring thy Brother: In a word, Thinke not in thy
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:21738:37"/> heart to be <hi>Accounted</hi> Good, much leſſe to <hi>Bee</hi> ſo, by doing Evill. But make way for <hi>New deſires,</hi> new <hi>Affections,</hi> and then <hi>New fruits</hi> will quickly follow: if once thou kindle this <hi>Coale</hi> of <hi>New Loue</hi> within, there will come forth a <hi>Flame;</hi> if <hi>New Thoughts,</hi> there will ſoone follow <hi>New words,</hi> and Actions: And 'twill be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the leſſe needfull to adde much concerning <hi>Theſe,</hi> and the <hi>Renewing</hi> of them; for, if the <hi>Thoughts</hi> of the Heart be once ſet <hi>right,</hi> our <hi>Words</hi> &amp; <hi>Actions</hi> are ſeldome out of order.</p>
            <p>Yet wee know, that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a <hi>coale</hi> (though quicke in it ſelfe) is vnhappily ſmoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:21738:37"/> before there breake forth a <hi>flame;</hi> a <hi>Fountaine</hi> now and then blocked vp, and ſo the <hi>current</hi> is loſt; good <hi>deſires</hi> many times corrupted; before they can proceede ſo farre as to appeare in our <hi>Speeches</hi> and <hi>Practiſes:</hi> for tis the <hi>preventing</hi> Policy of the Divill, if he can but once gueſſe at an intended Reformation in our <hi>Thoughts,</hi> to vſe all his miſchievous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, that ſo hee may ſtop it from going <hi>farther,</hi> and then tis loſt <hi>there</hi> too. It will not therefore bee amiſſe to ſhew farther in a word, that (for the <hi>perfecting</hi> of this <hi>Renovation</hi>) we muſt labour to <hi>reforme</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new</hi> our <hi>words</hi> and <hi>actions,</hi> as
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:21738:38"/> well as our <hi>Thoughts</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi> (to manifeſt vnto vs the Abuſes, that are vſuall in our <hi>Speech</hi>) diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſheth of a fiue fold <hi>Tongue.</hi> There is, ſaith he, <hi>Lingua impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dica, vaniloqua, doloſa, maledica, &amp; diſſoluta:</hi> An <hi>Immodeſt</hi> or <hi>Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſt</hi> Tongue; A <hi>vaine</hi> or <hi>fooliſh</hi> Tongue: A <hi>treacherous</hi> or <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull</hi> Tongue: A <hi>ſlaundring</hi> or <hi>iniurious</hi> Tongue: and, A <hi>diſſolute</hi> or <hi>Prophane</hi> Tongue.</p>
            <p>The Immodeſt or vnchaſt may be called a <hi>Fiery</hi> Tongue. <hi>Jam</hi> 3.6. for 'tis ſet on <hi>fire</hi> by the ſinfull <hi>Luſts</hi> and <hi>concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence,</hi> that is within: or elſe it may be tearmed an <hi>infectious,</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:21738:38"/> a <hi>poyſoning</hi> Tongue; becauſe it oft times ſtirreth vp <hi>vnchast deſires</hi> in thoſe, Which heare it. The vaine or fooliſh is a <hi>Perverſe</hi> Tongue <hi>Prov:</hi> 17.20. which will vtter all its folly, notwithſtanding any <hi>preiudice</hi> Whatſoever. The crafty or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull is a <hi>Lying</hi> Tongue, <hi>Prov</hi> 6.17. a <hi>flattering</hi> Tongue, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.9. a <hi>Double</hi> Tongue, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.8. the ſlaundring or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious is a <hi>Scourging</hi> tongue: <hi>Iob:</hi> 5.21. a <hi>Sharpe</hi> tongue <hi>Pſal.</hi> 140.3. a tongue <hi>whetted like a ſword: Pſal:</hi> 64.3. And the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute or Prophane is an <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridled,</hi> a <hi>Raging</hi> tongue <hi>Hoſ</hi> 7.16. a tongue that will needs <hi>prevaile</hi> againſt God Himſelfe;
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:21738:39"/> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 12.4. And all <hi>Theſe</hi> Tongues too often ſounde loud amongſt vs. In our <hi>Spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches</hi> then we haue a <hi>Large ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect</hi> for a <hi>Reformation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Paſſe wee from Theſe vnto our <hi>Actions,</hi> &amp; wee ſhall finde <hi>them</hi> as <hi>differently evill,</hi> as are our <hi>thoughts</hi> and <hi>words:</hi> for, as there is a <hi>luſtfull thought,</hi> and an <hi>Immodeſt tongue,</hi> ſo is there an <hi>vnchaſt practiſe</hi> too: if the <hi>Heart conceiue,</hi> and the <hi>tongue vtter vanity, falſhood, wrong,</hi> or whatſoever of that ſort; there will not be wanting a <hi>Diligent Hand,</hi> and a <hi>ſwift foote</hi> to put the ſame in <hi>Execution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, to <hi>Reforme</hi> all this; &amp; ſo to become <hi>New;</hi> not only
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:21738:39"/> in our <hi>thoughts</hi> and <hi>deſires,</hi> but alſo in the <hi>Expreſſions</hi> of them, which are our <hi>words</hi> &amp; <hi>deeds:</hi> Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> rule (before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4) may ſerue as a full <hi>Direction. Putting away lying,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>speake every man truth vnto his neighbour: bee no more angry</hi> beyond meaſure: <hi>ſteale no more:</hi> Let <hi>no more cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt communications proceede from you, &amp;c.</hi> But, laying aſide whatſoever is hurtfull, take in ſteede thereof that golden chaine which the ſame A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle hath made, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22. Conſiſting of the fruits of the ſpirit; as <hi>loue, meekeneſſe,</hi> &amp; the reſt there mentioned, and (as the wiſe man exhorteth his
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:21738:40"/> ſonne, <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.21.) <hi>binde it vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thy Heart, tie it about thy necke;</hi> for, when thou goeſt, it ſhall <hi>leade</hi> thee, when thou ſleepeſt, it ſhall <hi>keepe</hi> thee; when thou awakeſt, it ſhall <hi>talke</hi> With thee, and make thee accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the ſight of God. Then ſhalt thou be renewed whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and then maieſt thou with comfort ſay vnto thy ſoule, that <hi>All things are become new,</hi> when <hi>thou thy ſelfe</hi> art become <hi>New</hi> in All.</p>
            <p>And, being once <hi>thus Recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,</hi> knowe that in the laſt place there muſt bee <hi>studium ſanctè progrediendi;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore reſolue (as God ſhall ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thee) ever to continue ſo:
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:21738:40"/> for as wee muſt be <hi>cleanſed,</hi> &amp; become <hi>Holy;</hi> ſo muſt wee likewiſe labour to <hi>perfect</hi> holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh. 2 <hi>Cor</hi> 7.1: Now <hi>finis coronat o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus;</hi> tis the <hi>end,</hi> that brings <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection;</hi> and tis <hi>continuance,</hi> a well guided <hi>perſeverance</hi> that muſt reach vnto the <hi>end:</hi> wherefore, be <hi>New</hi> to <hi>Day,</hi> but remaine ſo to <hi>morrow</hi> too: become <hi>New this yeare,</hi> but let the next yeare finde thee <hi>ſuch;</hi> and then maiſt thou truly ſay that thou art become in <hi>All things,</hi> and <hi>Alwaies,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>perfectly new.</hi> The <hi>meanes,</hi> whereby the ſame may be ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, are in the next place to be conſidered.</p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:21738:41"/>
            <p>Theſe <hi>meanes</hi> are diverſe; but there are two rules in the Scripture, which will direct vs vnto the principall thereof. The firſt is recorded by <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Prov.</hi> 19.15. <hi>An Jdle ſoule,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>ſhall ſuffer hunger:</hi> the ſecond is mentioned by Saint <hi>Iames c.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 17. <hi>Every good and perfect gift is from aboue.</hi> The firſt rule holdeth true, as in matters <hi>Temporall,</hi> ſo likewiſe <hi>Spirituall:</hi> in Both, if a ſoule be idle, it ſhall <hi>ſuffer hunger,</hi> it ſhall alwaies bee in want: It may ſeemingly deſire, Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and thirſt after goodneſſe; but, if it <hi>Labour</hi> not to obtaine the ſame, it ſhall ſtill be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it. Our firſt <hi>meanes</hi> then is
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:21738:41"/> our owne <hi>Endeavour:</hi> we muſt <hi>Labour</hi> and bee <hi>diligent</hi> in <hi>fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenting conſcionably</hi> the Houſe of God; in making <hi>right vſe</hi> of his <hi>Word,</hi> and in <hi>Communicating conſtantly</hi> at his table for <hi>Theſe meanes</hi> will both <hi>direct</hi> vs <hi>vnto,</hi> and <hi>confirme</hi> and <hi>stay</hi> vs <hi>Jn</hi> our <hi>Newneſſe</hi> of life. But withall wee muſt remember, that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good and perfect gift is from <hi>Aboue,</hi> wherefore in the next place wee muſt betake our ſelues by <hi>earneſt prayer</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God; Which is the ſecond <hi>meanes;</hi> and neceſſarily requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to make the <hi>former</hi> effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: for tis not ſaid here, that <hi>wee</hi> doe <hi>make</hi> all things <hi>New;</hi> but that they are <hi>Become</hi> or
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:21738:42"/> 
               <hi>made new</hi> for vs. The <hi>word</hi> in the originall (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, are <hi>become</hi>) noteth (as moſt obſerue) an act of <hi>Creation;</hi> a <hi>Creation,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Aquinas</hi> on this Chapter) not of <hi>Nature</hi> but of Grace; and that, not the <hi>firſt grace of Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> in our <hi>converſion;</hi> for that is preſuppoſed to be done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: but a ſecond of <hi>Sanctity</hi> in our <hi>Converſation,</hi> which is here meant. Both belong vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God alone; for <hi>Hee</hi> only can <hi>Renew</hi> the <hi>Heart</hi> of man both by <hi>converſion</hi> and <hi>ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> who did firſt <hi>Create</hi> &amp; <hi>make</hi> it. Hence the Prayer of <hi>David</hi> was; that God would <hi>Create</hi> in him a <hi>New</hi> heart to feare him: and wee muſt alſo
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:21738:42"/> Pray, and that <hi>Earneſtly</hi> (if we will become New men to God) that God will be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to make his <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments</hi> powerfull &amp; effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all in vs, and perfect our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to the ſanctifying &amp; <hi>Renewing</hi> of the ſoule.</p>
            <p>Herevnto we might adde a 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
               <hi>meanes;</hi> and that is in the courſe of our liues the <hi>choyce</hi> of <hi>Such company,</hi> as will deſire &amp; ſeeke to become <hi>New</hi> with vs; which indeede is both pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable and neceſſary: for Hee, that ſtill aſſociateth himſelfe with <hi>Blaspheamers,</hi> with men of a <hi>Diſſolute, Slaundring,</hi> or <hi>fooliſh Tongue,</hi> muſt not thinke to caſt off &amp; leaue at pleaſure
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:21738:43"/> his cuſtome of <hi>ſwearing,</hi> of <hi>backebiting,</hi> of <hi>Immodest</hi> or <hi>Idle</hi> talking: in vaine doe men hope to bee <hi>Sober</hi> amongſt <hi>Drunkards;</hi> and tis little availe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to pretend Honeſty, as long as we caſt in our <hi>Lot,</hi> and haue <hi>one purſe</hi> with thoſe, that are <hi>Deceitfull.</hi> Evill <hi>communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt good manners; and the <hi>infection</hi> of <hi>Diſſolute companions</hi> perverteth <hi>Honest</hi> Deſires: if wee therefore will become <hi>New</hi> our ſelues, wee muſt not walke in the way with Thoſe, who ſtill deſire to remaine in their old ſinnes.</p>
            <p>Thus haue wee for Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſeene both the <hi>Manner,</hi> &amp;
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:21738:43"/> alſo the <hi>Meanes</hi> of this <hi>Renova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> we are now in the fourth and laſt place to conſider the <hi>fruits,</hi> thence ariſing, by way of <hi>Encouragement</hi> to the more <hi>ſpeedy</hi> and <hi>chearefull</hi> perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance thereof.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Laban</hi> would allure <hi>Iacob</hi> vnto his Service, his <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument,</hi> to <hi>encourage</hi> him, was that hee ſhould not ſerue him for nothing, and therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of him what (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his owne deſire) his wages ſhould bee <hi>Gen.</hi> 29.15. If the World were as rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to <hi>perſwade</hi> true ſeruice, or to <hi>recompence</hi> the ſame where they finde it, they which la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, would happily find leſſe
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:21738:44"/> cauſe to obiect the <hi>withholding</hi> of their <hi>Hire,</hi> then ſometimes they doe. But let <hi>Mortality</hi> faile (as it ever hath and will doe) tis notwithſtanding of all moſt certaine, that <hi>God</hi> is <hi>Bountifull</hi> and <hi>changeth</hi> not: yet the <hi>Divell</hi> himſelfe (who ſeldome ſpeaketh true, never for the loue of Truth) even he will let vs know that <hi>Iob</hi> did not ſerue God for nothing <hi>Iob.</hi> 1.9. Never yet was any man the <hi>Worſe</hi> (what ever in our <hi>ſlothfull ſecurity</hi> and <hi>carnall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licateneſſe</hi> we may &amp; doe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceiue) I ſay never any man the <hi>worſe,</hi> but many Degrees <hi>bettered</hi> by the Service of God duly performed. To runne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:21738:44"/> punctually the <hi>Fruits</hi> thereof, were to enlarge this diſcourſe into a ſecond Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. One may ſerue for all the reſt (being indeede as much as all) namely, that, if we become <hi>New</hi> and <hi>Amende</hi> our liues as we ought, our God is thereby <hi>Glorified:</hi> for ſo ſpeaketh our <hi>Sauiour, Mat:</hi> 5.16. <hi>Let your light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee your good workes, and glorifie your Father which is in Heaven:</hi> Our <hi>good workes,</hi> our <hi>Newneſſe</hi> in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation is that which tendeth vnto the <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> of God; which (if rightly conſidered) cannot but be, to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:21738:45"/> a truly <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> to a <hi>Religious</hi> and <hi>Filiall</hi> Heart, the <hi>Summe</hi> of all <hi>Fruits,</hi> the <hi>vtmoſt,</hi> the <hi>Only</hi> end of all Endeavours. And ſurely (conſidering hoW Vnworthy of our ſelues wee are, and how <hi>little</hi> acceptance our beſt righteouſneſſe, for its owne deſerts, might looke to finde at the handes of God, it being (as the Prophet <hi>Jſaiah</hi> ſpeaketh) but as ſo many filthy ragges, &amp; ſo no way profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, no way acceptable) I ſay, conſidering this, tis encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement enough (if any will ſuffice) for vs, ſinfull Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talls, to become <hi>New crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> namely, that God willbe pleaſed <hi>Thereby</hi> to be Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:21738:45"/>
            <p>Yet, if the <hi>Weakeneſſe</hi> of <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality</hi> either can or will looke no farther then <hi>our ſelues,</hi> wee ſhall <hi>There</hi> likewiſe ſee <hi>vnpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel'd Profit; Benefits,</hi> that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be equall'd. If any man ſhall aske me, what they are? I will anſwere him; they are all compriſed in <hi>This one,</hi> the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving</hi> of the <hi>Soule,</hi> the <hi>drawing</hi> of it out, as it were, from the <hi>Bondage</hi> of ſinne to that <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Liberty,</hi> that <hi>Happineſſe</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible, which Chriſt hath purchaſed with his owne Blood.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Theſe</hi> or any <hi>Other</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements (though none more ſtrong) can now per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade and allure vs to <hi>Renew</hi>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:21738:46"/> our converſations before our God, then ſhall wee moſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily <hi>offer</hi> vp our ſelues an <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable ſacrifice,</hi> a <hi>Sanctified Gift</hi> vnto God, that lookes for it. And happy that Man, who ſhall <hi>thus</hi> diſpoſe of his owne ſoule: for if wee ſhall Thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>New</hi> in all things, then ſhall All things become <hi>New</hi> to vs: Wee ſhall haue in <hi>This</hi> life <hi>new Mercies, new Bleſſings;</hi> or rather, the <hi>old Mercies,</hi> and <hi>Favours</hi> of <hi>God Renewed</hi> to vs; And, when this life ſhall bee no more, we ſhall haue <hi>New Heavens,</hi> wherein wee ſhall, with a <hi>New</hi> company of <hi>Saints</hi> and Angells, ſing for ever a <hi>New ſong</hi> of <hi>reioycing</hi>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:21738:46"/> vnto our God, in whoſe ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice We became <hi>New creatures</hi> here on earth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou O Lord, who alone ſeeſt the hearts of all men, knoweſt that we are all full of corruption; and can of our ſelues doe nothing but ſinne; be pleaſed therefore, O Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Mercy; to make thy good word powerfull in vs to the caſting downe of ſinne and the Devices thereof, that ſo wee may thence learne to Renew our Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons before Thee; and, by thy Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting Grace, to bring forth the fruits of an Holy life, in ſome Thirty, in ſome Sixty, in ſome an Hundred fold, to the Glory of Thy name and the Salvation of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:21738:47"/> our owne ſoules, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord and only Saviour. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Glory bee to GOD. Good will towards Men.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21738:47"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21738:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
